### **PAUL BOUVIER**

Chemin de la Combe 7, CH- 1272 Genolier

Phone: +4178 625 49 48

E-Mail: <a href="mailto:paul.bouvier@alumni.ethz.ch">paul.bouvier@alumni.ethz.ch</a>



# PROJECT AND BUSINESS MANAGER - ENGINEER ETH ZURICH - MBA EM LYON

Results oriented business leader with 20+ years experience in industry B2B and consulting, business and technical roles, process and manufacturing industries, and regulated environments. Focused on business decisions and its implementation, on crafting ad-hoc processes and related services, developing and coaching teams, performing technical sales, coordinating engineering and product development, supervising product/service launch. Experienced in entrepreneurial teams as well as in corporate surroundings.

Projects Lifecycle: Conduct international projects, implementing solutions towards objectives, from customer requirements phase up to verification, commissioning and solution validation. Coordinate development engineering and teams, through MVP and up-to industrialized systems and solutions.

Strategy & Business Development: Assess, adapt, identify and drive new and bespoke products, services and business models. Monitor products and projects portfolio. Perform technical sales and manage trustworthy customer relationships.

Operations: Lead process design and improvement projects (industrial network design, plant production capacity maximization, optimized production planning and scheduling, debottlenecking, inventory policies). Implement new corporate processes (organization level) and good practices (e.g. for development, project management, servicing, sales), quality focus and compliance to regulations.

Management: Ability to motivate and coach internal and customer project teams, develop trustworthy customer relationships, acquire and secure resources, perform line management, implement best in class solutions in organizations seeking change.

# **Working Experience:**

Company:

SICPA SA - Lausanne - Prilly, Switzerland

2011 - 2017

Positions:

Project Manager

**Quality Coordinator** 

Activity:

SICPA is privately owned and a world leader in security solutions, for banknotes or industrial products, serving governments or industries, providing complex integrated systems, enabling product authentication, end-user safety, and against counterfeiting and

smuggling.

Assignment:

Manage and support Projects for Pharma. accounts.

Develop internal processes to be Pharma. (regulatory) compliant.

Train (internally) and continuously support the development of SICPA as a qualified supplier

for Pharma.

Accomplishment:

- Developed and matured PMO for a new SICPA Division (Pharma. compliant, GAMP inspired), PMO portfolio monitoring up to 50 projects.
- Constructed divisional Quality System, involving R&D, IT & Hardware Development (including Agile and Scrum), Sales & Marketing, Project Management, Operations and Servicing), coached stakeholders and managed system ISO certification (9001 / 14001 / 18001) as well as Pharma. customers audits (GAMP referential).
- Supported sales negotiation with Pharma. customers leading to R&D projects, prototyping and industrializations.
- Led projects for industrial customers (R&D concepts, prototypes, industrializations, or product customizations). Solutions are automated systems, e.g. integrating front-end SW and equipment (mechanics, vision, electronics, printing units, chemical security features and special inks), back-end system and database.
- Coordinated Product developments, adapted processes to emerging standardization, sustained quality and Pharma. compliance (e.g. led risk analysis for design).
- Conducted Quality Assurance, approved testing, led process improvements and provided internal training (e.g. for Pharma. good practices).

Paul Bouvier 1/3



Company: ORTEC-Brightrivers SA – Lausanne, Switzerland

Principal Consultant

Co-Owner and Administrator

Project Manager

Activity: Brightrivers SA, a Swiss (consulting and SaaS) firm specialized in decision help services for

process industries (Pharma., Food, Cosmetics, Health Care). In 2007, ORTEC (consulting and SaaS in The Netherlands), specialized in distribution planning and outbound logistics,

2002 - 2011

acquires Brightrivers.

Assignment: Manage and conduct consulting projects.

Supervise internally Junior and Senior Consultants and drive customer project teams.

Assist the General Manager in Business Development.

Accomplishment:

Positions:

 Headed projects at Migros, L'Oreal, Dipharma-Francis, Nestlé, Nespresso, Invacare, Owens-Illinois, Johnson & Johnson, Roche, TNT Post, Dr. Reddys., Carlsberg, World Food Programme.

 Completed solution scenarios including trade-offs quantification for optimized Supply-Chain design, advanced planning featuring high process accuracy, plant production and process improvements, and distribution network design.

Worked effectively and demonstrated push-pull equilibriums, bottlenecks in complex plants, maximizing capacity acting on campaign sizes and sequencing, balancing production (lot sizes) versus inventories, identifying optimal equipment use between multi-purpose and dedication.

• Evaluated network capacity dimensioning, optimal routes and product flows, as well as dimensioning of hubs, regional warehouses, up to distribution centers.

 Negotiated, winning projects (Johnson & Johnson Italy then USA, Migros Aproz, Mibelle).

Conducted support trainings to customers.

**Deloitte.** 

Company: **Deloitte** – Lyon, France 2000 – 2002

Position: <u>Senior Consultant</u>

Activity: Service line for Industry, specialized in Supply-Chain, IT and ERP deployment, Operations

and Inventory services.

Assignment: <u>Project Management for IT</u>, ERP implementation.

Manufacturing and Supply-Chain improvement (industry and retail, France, Switzerland,

Italy).

Accomplishment:

 Managed process reengineering (e.g. separate & streamline flows according to complexity or dedication of activities) and designed KPIs (e.g. OEE).

• Identified inventory reductions (e.g. improved forecasting, order launching, refined target inventories or inventory location), gain in information accuracy and processing.

Organized projects and hold workshops for IT - ERP deployments (from functional analysis to parametrization)

analysis to parametrization).



Company: **EPI SA** – Belgium 1996 – 1999

Positions: <u>Junior Consultant</u>, then <u>Senior Consultant</u>

Activity: EPI SA (Belgium) is a boutique productivity improvement consulting firm, implementing

costs reductions (for multinationals to medium sized companies, Industry and Service

sectors).

Assignment: <u>Implemented operations management</u>, process design with KPI's.

Cost improvement programmes. Pre-sales consulting analysis.

Paul Bouvier 2/3

### Accomplishment:

- Developed and matured shop floor operational process implementations (validated recurring cost savings, decreased cycle times, improved measured productivity and service level, enhanced planning and reporting).
- Performed consulting analysis in 50 Companies (Germany, Switzerland, Belgium, France, The Netherlands), assessing operations performance in production-, maintenance-, warehouses-, sales-, purchasing-areas, or other administration departments.
- Launched a new consulting office & supervised telemarketing activity (Germany).



Company: CMD – Fourchambault, France

1995 - 1996

Position:

Product Engineer for mechanical gears manufacturing (customized solutions)



Company: **Gerland** – Montelimar, France then Wiesbaden, Germany

1992 – 1995

Positions:

Quality Engineer, production of plastic hoses, France, then

Sales (plastic hoses), Germany, then

IT Engineer, integrated software implementation, Germany

#### **Education:**

**ETH Zürich** (Swiss Federal Institute of Technology) – Zürich, Switzerland

1987 - 1992

**Engineer** (Mechanics)

EM Lyon (Management school) - Lyon, France

1999 - 2000

Executive MBA (Full time programme)

### **Certification:**

PMI - PMP (Project Management Institute, certified as Project Management Professional)

2018

**EPFL Extension School** – 50 Things You Need to Know About the Internet

2018

### Languages & Multicultural skills:

French Mother tongue

German Excellent knowledge (studies at ETH in German, plus several years in Germany)
English Excellent knowledge (MBA studies in English, and working language since 1996)

Italian Good knowledge

# Personal data:

Married, 2 children

Dual nationalities: Swiss / French

Paul Bouvier 3/3